Finding Aid for American Friends Service Committee. Michigan Area Office records, 1956-2002
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
American Friends Service Committee. Michigan Area Office records 1956-2002 1970-2000
American Friends Service Committee. Michigan Area Office.
85478 Ba 2; Ba Outsize
Michigan office of national organization concerned with peace, poverty, and other matters of social justice. Administrative files, topical files, and regional and national office materials; contain files relating to their interest in pacifism, draft counseling, community service, prison reform and other issues relating to the criminal justice system, and peace education (especially relating to the Middle East and the conflict between Israel and the Palestinians), and lesbian/gay issues.
23 linear feet
1 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records were received from the Michigan Area Office (donor no. 4997 ) in multiple accessions beginning in 1971.
Periodic additions to the records are expected.
The record group is open to research.
The American Friends Service Committee (AFSC) was established in 1917 during World War I as an outreach program of the Quakers, offering humanitarian aid to the war's victims. From the beginning, there has been a strong vein of dissent in Quaker outreach activities, protesting against abuse while caring for those who suffer.
In 1960, the Michigan Area Office (MAO) of the American Friends Service Committee (AFSC) came into being in response to a concern from Friends in Michigan to expand AFSC programs beyond the volunteer youth service activities which had been going on in the 1950s. From the outset, the MAO sought to serve as many Michigan communities as possible through its peace education and youth service programs and projects. In 1972, the Michigan Area Executive Committee (MAEC), in conjunction with staff, developed a plan to establish a Western Michigan Program Office, and in 1975 the MAEC founded the Detroit Program Office.
As of the 1970-1971 fiscal year, the MAO was made up of an executive committee, community relations committee, and peace education committee. The executive committee was responsible for making major policy decisions and providing overall leadership and review for programs in Michigan. The community relations committee and the peace education committee provided leadership and oversight for the programs within their respective domains.
While the basic structure remained the same, the Michigan Area Office did undergo a few organizational changes since that time. In 1977, a restructuring subcommittee of the MAO clarified the position of the MAEC and changed the Michigan Area Program Secretary's title to Michigan Area Executive Secretary. (It appears the Michigan Area Executive Committee was previously known as the Michigan Area Program Committee.) This subcommittee also stated that the program committees--peace education and community relations--were responsible for defining policy areas, developing programming methods, identifying resources needed, and presenting these to the MAEC. Besides the two program committees, the MAEC was supported by personnel and nominating committees.
Apparently the Michigan Area Executive Committee went through another name change or restructuring, since a later organizational chart shows the MAO as headed by a committee called the Michigan Area Coordinating Committee (MACC). This chart, which appears to be from the mid-1980s, indicates that the MACC was supported by the same four subordinate committees mentioned previously in relation to the MAEC.
Although the Michigan Area Office was originally subordinate to the Dayton Regional Office (DRO), the DRO and the Midwest Regional Office merged in 1985 to create the Great Lakes Regional Office. An organizational chart shows that Dayton became the seat of an area office, which, with the MAO and the Chicago Area Office, was subordinate to the new Great Lakes Regional Office. The national office, which oversees nine regional offices, is based in Philadelphia.
According to a 1986 statement, the mission of the American Friends Service Committee is "to help express the historic Peace Testimony of Friends and Friends' commitments to equality, simplicity, peace and justice. These are founded in Friends' belief that every person possesses that of God within herself or himself, and is a person of worth and dignity." The Michigan Area Office of the AFSC employed a small staff and relied on many volunteers to carry out its programs. The MAO Peace Education Committee (MAPEC) was especially active in Middle Eastern issues, and was led in this work by staff members Joe Volk and Richard Cleaver. Barbara Cartwright and Marc Mauer led the MAO Community Relations Committee (MACRC), which focused its work on increasing equity in the criminal justice system (especially regarding bail). In the 1990s, the organization began working on issues relating to discrimination against gays, lesbians, and bisexuals.
The records of the Michigan Area Office of the American Friends Service Committee have been arranged into the followings series: Executive Committee / Coordinating Committee; Peace Education Committee; Community Relations Committee; National and Regional Offices; Administrative files; Topical files; and Audio-Visual Materials.
Subjects:
American Friends Service Committee. Michigan Area Office.; Bail--Michigan.; Criminal justice, Administration of--Michigan.; Jewish-Arab relations.; Michigan Coalition Against the Death Penalty.; Draft.; Pacifism.; Peace--Societies, etc.; Prison reformers--Michigan.; Prisons--Overcrowding--Michigan.; Society of Friends--Michigan.; Prisons--Michigan.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
African Americans--Michigan.; American Friends Service Committee. Michigan Area Office.; Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Demonstrations.; Church work.; Demonstrations--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Pacifists--Michigan.; Quakers--Michigan.; Royal Oak (Mich.: Township); Slums--Michigan--Royal Oak (Township)
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Executive Committee / Coordinating Committee
  Since the executive committee and its successor, the coordinating committee, served as the overall policy and administrative unit for the MAO, the files in this series contain materials documenting--and often explaining--the overall functioning and policy development of the MAO. The minutes, extending from 1979 to 1988, document policy and management issues and decisions and are an important beginning to understanding the mission and work of the MAO. Minutes after 1988 were not maintained separately and thus are scattered throughout other record series.
  - Minutes (Executive Committee) 1974-October 1980, 5 folders (Box 1)
  - Minutes (Michigan Area Coordinating Committee) 1982-1988, 7 folders (Box 1)
- Peace Education Committee
  The Peace Education Committee series consists of two chronological subseries and three subseries of records maintained by PEC coordinators and secretaries. The great value of this series is its documentation of the issues of the time and the response of the MAO to these issues. Of special interest is the PEC's Middle East Peace Education program. The PEC was especially active in educating about the Palestinian-Israeli conflict and seeking peaceful resolution to tensions arising from that situation. Included is a near-complete run of the newsletter, "Middle East Peace Notes," that runs from 1976 to 1987. The PEC also sponsored and arranged extensive lectures, conferences, and seminars regarding Middle Eastern issues. Speakers who participated in the lecture series included Jim Fine, Everett Mendelssohn, Mattityahu Peled, and Loren Tesdell. The subseries maintained by Coordinator/Peace Education Secretaries, Joe Volk, (1977-1982) Richard Cleaver (1982-1992), and Area Coordinator Jan Wright (1992-2002) also contain additional information about Peace in the Middle East and Militarism and Non-violence. One issue that came to the fore in the 1990s concerned protection of the rights of lesbian/gay/bisexual citizens. A significant portion of Jan Wright subseries relates to workshops and conferences on this topic sponsored by the organization.
  - 1974-1979
    - Administration
      - General, 11 folders (Box 1)
      - Minutes 1972-1979 (Box 1)
      - Correspondence 1976-1977 (Box 1)
      - Interns in Community Service (Detroit) 1975-1977 (Box 1)
      - Committee for Humanizing Society 1976
        - General Papers (Box 1)
        - Peace Conversion Conference April 9, 1976
          - General (Box 1)
          - Documents for Planning (Box 1)
          - Full Employment Planning Committee (Box 1)
          - Regional Decentralization Planning Committee (Box 1)
          - Committee for Humanizing Society (Box 1)
      - Demonstration (Detroit AFSC) April 15-November 10, 1975 (Box 1)
      - Peace Curriculum and Conflict Resolution 1973-1976 (Box 1)
      - Miscellaneous Program Materials 1975-1976 (Box 1)
  - 1979-1987 (includes some earlier material)
    - Administration
      - Budget 1981-1982 (Box 2)
      - Committee Nominations 1981-1982 (Box 2)
      - Committee Rosters 1986-1987 (Box 2)
      - Disarmament: Deadly Connections Task Force 1982-1984 (Box 2)
      - Evaluation/Planning 1985-1986 (Box 2)
      - Indochina Subcommittee 1982 (Box 2)
      - Intern (consideration) 1981 (Box 2)
      - Internship Evaluation 1982 (Box 2)
      - Job Description 1982 (Box 2)
      - Joint Work with YWCA: Great Decision Group 1986 (Box 2)
      - Mailings and Miscellaneous Reports and Statements 1980-1987, 8 folders (Box 2)
      - Michigan Peace Education Collection (office library catalog) circa 1985 (Box 2)
      - Minutes 1980-1987, 8 folders (Box 2)
      - Peace Education Literature Orders, etc. 1978-1979 (Box 2)
      - Program Activities Reports 1978-1982 (partial) (Box 2)
      - Program Planning 1979-1986 (partial) (Box 2)
      - Program on Militarism and Nonviolence 1986-1987 (Box 2)
      - Program Review and Evaluation 1985 (Box 2)
      - Reports: Nationwide Peace Ed. Committee Meeting 1978, 1981 (Box 2)
      - Retreat September 1985 (Box 2)
      - Secretary's Reports 1982 (Box 2)
      - Staff Reports 1982-1986 (Box 2)
    - Eastern Michigan Peace Education Committee (EMPEC)
      - Budget 1979-1980 (Box 2)
      - Disarmament Paper November 1979 (Box 2)
      - Letter to the Editor (Regarding U.S. hostages in Iran) April 1980 (Box 2)
      - Mailings/Materials 1977-1980, 6 folders (Box 2)
      - Minutes 1978-1980 (partial) (Box 2)
      - Nominations 1980-1981 (Box 2)
      - Peru Project 1979 (Box 2)
    - Topical File 1977-1986
      - "Amerika" Miniseries 1986 (Box 2)
      - Cambodian Peace Education Proposal 1980 (Box 2)
      - Committee to Affirm Human Dignity and Freedom March 1982 (Box 2)
      - Defense Research at the University of Michigan 1982-1983 (Box 2)
      - El Salvador 1980 (Box 2)
      - "Nomad" Doll 1986 (Box 2)
      - Peace Caravans 1982 (Box 2)
      - Poland 1980-1982 (Box 2)
      - Racism Workshop/Panel April 1986 (Box 2)
      - South Africa 1977-1978 (Box 2)
      - Tri-Cities Peace Coalition 1982 (Box 2)
      - United Methodist Church Peace Week Materials 1986 (Box 2)
  - International and national topics 1973-1987
    - Indochina
      - Appeal for Reconciliation 1976 (Box 2)
      - Correspondence 1976 (Box 2)
      - Humanitarian Aid
        - Act for Friendship (Vietnam)
          - Correspondence 1975-1976 (Box 2)
          - Evaluations 1976 (Box 2)
        - Friends of Indochina 1975 (Box 2)
        - Sweaters for Vietnam 1973-1976 (Box 2)
      - Indochina Task Force/Indochina Program 1974-1975, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - Summer Project in Indiana 1975 (Box 2)
    - Middle East Peace Education
      - Administrative
        - Biographical Sketches (Joe Volk, Howard Alexander, Nelson Brown, Jr., Carolyn Chapman), ca. 1975 (Box 2)
        - Budgetary Materials 1975-1976 (Box 2)
        - Correspondence
          - Alexander, Howard 1975-1976 (Box 2)
          - Chapman, Virginia 1975-1977 (Box 2)
          - Middle East Policy (U.S.) 1977-1978 (Box 2)
        - Disarmament Intern 1981 (Box 2)
        - Dayton Regional Office (DRO)
          - Correspondence/Miscellaneous 1971-1977, 4 folders (Box 2)
          - Middle East Working Group 1975-1976 (Box 2)
          - Peace Education Proposal 1976-1977 (Box 2)
          - Program Reports 1977 (Box 2)
        - Field Staff Reports 1975-1976 (Box 3)
        - Gund Foundation Proposal 1977-1980, 3 folders (Box 3)
        - Jobs Memorandum (Responsibilities for Communication) 1980 (Box 3)
        - Meeting March 12, 1983 (Box 3)
        - Middle East Panel Meeting 1987 (Box 3)
        - Mid. East Program Proposal
          - Background 1980 (Box 3)
          - Michigan Council for the Humanities Grant 1980 (Box 3)
        - Miscellaneous Memos and Statements 1985-1988 (Box 3)
        - Miscellaneous Press Releases 1980-1983 (Box 3)
        - Position Description 1982 (Box 3)
        - Post-Conference Meeting April 30, 1979 (Box 3)
        - Report to the American Friends Service Committee Board of Directors 1983 (Box 3)
        - Staff Lectures
          - 1981-1982 (Box 3)
          - 1984-1985 (Box 3)
        - Workplan July-October 1985 (Box 3)
      - Conferences
        - Birmingham, MI Conference on Middle East October 1979
          - Materials (Box 3)
          - Evaluations (Box 3)
        - "Can an Israeli State and a Palestinian State Coexist?" 1977-1978
          - Materials (Box 3)
          - Evaluations (Box 3)
        - Dayton: Conference on Middle East 1977 (Box 3)
        - Jewish Peace Tour 1987 (Box 3)
        - Middle East Peace Week October 1985 (Box 3)
        - Perilous New Directions 1980
          - Materials (Box 3)
          - Evaluations (Box 3)
        - U.S. Policy after Camp David 1979 (Box 3)
        - Washington, D.C. (Chevy Chase, MD), National Middle East Conference 1977 (Box 3)
      - Miscellaneous
        - Clippings: Persian Gulf Conflict & Israeli Invasion of Lebanon 1984 (Box 3)
        - Coalition for a New Foreign and Military Policy Position Paper (Regarding Middle East) 1982 (Box 3)
        - A Compassionate Peace (American Friends Service Committee book), 1982 (Box 3)
        - Draft, Middle East Peace Alternative, Policy and Action Proposal 1985 (Box 3)
        - Fine, Jim: "The Tragedy of Lebanon" (article) 1981 (Box 3)
        - Gerson, Joe: "Guarantees for Middle East Peace," 1977 (Box 3)
        - Iran-Iraq War, article by Joseph Gerson 1980 (Box 3)
        - Iran/U.S. Hostages, Mailing December 1980 (Box 3)
        - Jensen, Carol and Ron Young: Letters from the Middle East, Nos. 1-15 1982-1985 (Box 3)
        - Letter to the Editor Regarding West Bank 1982 (Box 3)
        - Libya Memorial Service & American Friends Service Committee Statements Regarding U.S. Attack 1986 (Box 3)
        - PBS Frontline of November 13, 1984 (regarding speakers tour co-sponsored by American Friends Service Committee) (Box 3)
        - Radio Transcript 1977 (Jewish leader mentions American Friends Service Committee) (Box 3)
        - Reagan Admin., Qadafi/Libya Propaganda 1986 (Box 3)
        - Richardson, Betty, Report on Trip to Cuba 1969 (Box 3)
        - Women and Middle East Program Development 1976 (Box 3)
      - Publications
        - "Middle East Peace Notes," 1976-1987 (partial) (Box 3)
        - Miscellaneous (no dates) (Box 3)
      - Seminar Series
        - First Seminar October 1982, Essoyan, Catherine (Box 3)
        - Second Seminar December 1982, Collett, Wallace (Box 3)
        - Third Seminar February 1983, Holland, Max (Box 3)
        - Fourth Seminar April 1983, Fine, Jim (Box 3)
        - Fifth Seminar circa May 1983, Frank, Libby (Box 3)
      - Speakers
        - Ajami, Fouad 1977-1981 (Box 3)
        - Arenas, Richard 1983 (Box 3)
        - Bar-On, Mordecai, Mounir Fasheh, and Mohammed Milhem 1984 (Box 3)
        - Berger, Tamara, and Rita Giocaman 1984 (Box 3)
        - Brinker, Menachem 1978-1979 (Box 3)
        - Broomfield, John 1980 (Box 3)
        - Collett, Wallace 1982 (Box 3)
        - Eliav, Arie 1977 (Box 3)
        - El-Asmar, Fouzi 1978-1979 (Box 3)
        - Fine, Deborah and Jim 1979-1981 (Box 3)
        - George, Chris 1984 (Box 3)
        - Hanover, Ned 1976 (Box 3)
        - Hart, Alan 1985-1986 (Box 3)
        - Holland, Max 1979 (Box 3)
        - Kelman, Herbert 1978-1979 (Box 3)
        - Koenig, Shula 1979 (Box 3)
        - Kuttab, Jonathan 1981 (Box 3)
        - Lesch, Ann 1977 (Box 3)
        - Levy, Bob 1976 (Box 3)
        - Mendelssohn, Everett 1982 (Box 3)
        - Milhem, Mohammed 1978 (Box 3)
        - Nixon, Anne 1985 (Box 3)
        - Pail, Meir circa 1980 (Box 3)
        - Peled, Mattityahu 1976-1980 (Box 3)
        - Peretz, Don 1979 (Box 3)
        - Shaham, David 1976-1977 (Box 4)
        - Sharabi, Hisham 1978 (Box 4)
        - Solomonow, Allan 1979-1980 (Box 4)
        - Spiro, Gideon 1986 (Box 4)
        - Tesdell, Loren 1976 (Box 4)
        - Tull, Carolyn 1979 (Box 4)
        - Tumas, Elias 1979 (Box 4)
        - Vogel, Bob 1975 (Box 4)
        - Volk, Joe 1975 (Box 4)
        - Wingerter, Rex 1979 (Box 4)
        - Yermiya, Dov 1985 (Box 4)
        - Young, Ron 1983-1985 (Box 4)
      - Task Force Meetings November 1978-September 1989 (partial), 12 folders (Box 4)
    - Military (U.S.) / Selective Service
      - Arms Buildup
        - Deadly Connections Task Force (Deadly Connections: The Links Between Interventionism, Social Oppression, and Nuclear War) 1984-1985 (Box 4)
        - Fallout Shelter 1962 ("Dear President Kennedy" letter) (Box 4)
        - Peace Conversion of Economy 1970-1980 (Box 4)
        - Sanguine/Seafarer (Military projects) 1975 (Box 4)
        - Stop the Anti-Ballistic Missile 1967-1973 (Box 4)
        - Stop the B-1 Bomber 1975-1976 (Box 4)
      - Racism in Peace Groups 1991 (Box 4)
      - Selective Service
        - Conscientious Objection Counselors List 1967 (Box 4)
        - Conscientious Objectors' Statements 1980-1981 (Box 4)
        - Draft Counseling Correspondence 1970-1986 (Box 4)
        - Fliers (American Friends Service Committee, Washtenaw Committee Against Registration and the Draft), early 1980s (Box 4)
        - Michigan Draft Information Exchange 1969-1972 (Box 4)
        - Washtenaw Committee Against Registration and the Draft
          - Correspondence 1980-1984, 3 folders (Box 4)
          - Correspondence with Legislators 1980-1982 (Box 4)
          - Miscellaneous Statements Undated (Box 4)
          - Newsletter, volumes 1-5 1981-1985, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - Writings, Richard Cleaver 1983-1987 (Box 4)
    - National Peace Education Committee (NPEC)
      - Discussion Paper, "That all May live together," 1981-1982 (Box 4)
      - Executive Committee 1984-1985 (Box 4)
      - Interim Committee Minutes March 1983 (Box 4)
      - Minutes and Materials, Meetings October 1982-May 1984, 5 folders (Box 4)
      - Miscellaneous 1983-1984, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - Response to New Republic Article, 1979 (Box 4)
      - Staff Consultative Group 1986 (Box 4)
      - U.S.-European Peace Tour 1982 (Box 4)
    - Speakers
      - Berryman, Phillip and Angela 1980 (Box 4)
      - Boulding, Elise October 1985 (Box 4)
      - Dumas, Lloyd J. 1979 (Box 4)
      - Easter, Maud and David October 8-9, 1979 (Box 4)
      - Henderson, Martha 1978 (Box 4)
      - Johnson, Corrine 1979 (Box 4)
      - Mendlovitz, Saul H. 1977 (Box 4)
      - Molineaux, David February 1980 (Box 4)
      - Moyer, Bill June 1985 (Box 4)
      - Provance, Terry February 1979 (Box 4)
      - Rodenko, Igal 1987 (Box 4)
      - Sutherland, Bill 1978 (Box 4)
  - MAPEC, Coordinator/Peace Education Secretary, Joe Volk, files 1977-1982
    - Letter of Appointment and Job Description (Volk) 1977 (Box 4)
    - MAPEC log, handwritten by Volk 1982-1983 (Box 4)
    - Meeting minutes 1979-1985 (scattered), 4 folders (Box 4)
    - Meetings and Conferences
      - Detroit Friends Meeting 1981 (Box 4)
      - Friends General Conference Middle East Workshop 1978 (Box 4)
      - Friends General Meeting, Ithaca, NY 1980 (Box 4)
      - Indiana Yearly Meeting 1979 (Box 4)
      - "Middle East: Between Peace and War", New Outlook International Symposium 1979 (Box 4)
      - "New Call to Peacemaking," October, 1980 (Box 4)
      - Quaker Hill: Midwest Friends Conference on the Middle East November 10-12, 1978 (Box 4)
      - "Religions and War", Manchester College, Spring 1979 (Box 4)
    - Topical files
      - Bill Sutherland tour and follow up 1978 (Box 4)
        (South Africa issue includes photo)
      - Black Americans in Support of Democracy and Peace on the African Continent 1978 (Box 4)
      - Center for Social Concerns, campus ministry 1978 (Box 4)
      - Detroit Edison Shareholders Initiative, endorsement 1978 (Box 4)
      - Green Pastures Quarterly Meeting 1978-1981 (scattered) (Box 5)
      - Levin, Senator Carl, correspondence (Box 5)
      - Middle East background materials 1981-1982 (Box 5)
      - Nuclear Challenge to Christian Conscience, (packet) (Box 5)
      - Purcell, Representative Carl, correspondence (Box 5)
      - "Tragedy of Lebanon," Spring 1981 (Box 5)
      - UAW Peace Conversation, Detroit (correspondence) 1978-1979 (Box 5)
    - Grant Award and Proposal, Michigan Council for the Humanities 1980 titled "Perilous New Directions: U.S. Soviet Confrontation in the Middle East and Central Asia" (Box 5)
    - Student Advocacy Center, Funding Proposal 1978 (Box 5)
  - MAPEC Coordinator/Peace Secretary, Richard Cleaver, files 1982-1992
    - Richard G. Cleaver, back ground information, articles, memos 1983-1992 (Box 5)
    - MAPEC minutes and memoranda 1985-1993 (some gaps), 4 folders (Box 5)
    - Topical files
      - Beyond Containment 1988 (Box 5)
      - Call to Action Against Racism 1992 (Box 5)
      - Children of War tour 1986 (Box 5)
      - Dealing with Drugs, Latin America, National Drug tour 1992 (Box 5)
      - Draft Resisters Defense Committee 1983-1984 (Box 5)
      - Homophobia and Militarism (position paper by RC) 1991 (Box 5)
      - Housing Policy, Gay and Lesbian 1990 (Box 5)
      - Job Security and National Security 1983 (Box 5)
      - LGARAC, Lesbian-Gay Anti-Racist Action Committee 1988 (Box 5)
      - Managua, Nicaragua Cathedral 1990-1991 (Box 5)
      - Nationwide AIDS Action (AIDS Demonstration), May 7,1988 (Box 5)
      - Nuclear Disarmament issue, cities' response
        - Adrian (Box 5)
        - Ann Arbor, 2 folders (Box 5)
        - Bay Area (Box 5)
        - Detroit (Box 5)
        - Flint (Box 5)
        - Grand Rapids (Box 5)
        - Hillsdale (Box 5)
        - Lansing, 2 folders (Box 5)
      - Pledge of Resistance 1990-1991 (Box 5)
      - Progressive Coalition 1989 (Box 5)
      - Resource Center for Non-Violence
        - Study Tour 1984 (Box 5)
        - Summer Workshop 1988 (Box 5)
      - Terrorism, background material 1984 (Box 5)
      - "To the Light of Human Conscience; Addressing Homophobia and Militarism from Our Spiritual Roots" 1992 (Box 5)
        (includes background material and RC's notes)
      - YWCA Great Decisions (Box 5)
    - Youth and Militarism
      - Correspondence, memoranda 1986-1992, 4 folders (Box 6)
      - Dellums Bill, Military Conscientious Objector Act 1992 (Box 6)
      - Joint Youth Project September, 1984-1985 (Box 6)
      - ROTC, Sexual Discrimination 1991-1992 (Box 6)
      - Youth and Militarism Task Force Meetings 1990-1992, 5 folders (Box 6)
    - Non-Violence
      - "Active Non-Violence in World Conflicts," April 1988 (Box 6)
      - Annual Program Review June 1988 (Box 6)
      - Brochure regarding program on Militarism and Non-Violence (Box 6)
      - Buford, Daniel, speaking tour on Racism and Militarism 1988 (Box 6)
      - Interfaith Council for Peace Steering Committee 1987 (Box 6)